Welcome back to Apush in under 3
minutes. No time for intros, let's get
into it. Lots of people throughout the
last century in American history have
been working in factories. I mean, it
was the whole point of the Gilded Age.
But now with the Cold War mostly over,
countries with a specific emphasis on
China are going to open up to trade. So
that begs the question, if it is cheaper
to globalize and pay Chinese workers to
produce goods rather than paying a lot
of money to American workers, why the
heck would any business stay localized
in America? And this will lead to one of
the biggest shifts in world history
called globalization, where businesses
operate globally, meaning companies can
produce goods in other countries and
there is a big trade increase. And
pretty quickly looking at the United
States, factory jobs dry up relatively
quickly. And now you see new age
technology come out at a very crucial
point. So that means now after the '80s,
the US job market will shift to mostly
encapsulate service jobs, meaning things
like retail, healthcare, finance,
education, or tech. This means how
people work, how businesses operate, and
how people communicate all drastically
change in a brief period. This also
means that labor unions dramatically
decline alongside factory jobs. And I
want to point out that this new
technology like the internet and
computers really does change everything.
For example, later you have social media
along with stuff like remote work
becoming a possibility. You also see a
spike in production because new
technology makes it so workers can
produce more in less time. But wherever
there is light, there is also darkness.
And here I want to talk about the bad
effects of this new generation. The
first here is that wages for middle and
working class Americans stagnated as
most economic gains increasingly went to
corporations and the top 1%. The second
thing here though is a digital divide.
Because I want you to imagine that lots
of older folks who aren't prone to
changing their ways or might not have
access to the new tech could potentially
not adopt the new technological changes.
So that means some people benefit a lot
from the new tech economy while many
others are left behind. That will be all
for this one. On the screen now are AP
style questions for this topic. Pause
now.
I'll put the answers on the screen now.
Only two more to go after this.